Guide to the Frank Lovell Papers TAM.204
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frank Lovell Papers
1953-1999
1970-1997
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lovell, Frank
TAM.204
11.94 Linear Feet in 9 record cartons and 6 manuscript boxes
Frank Lovell was born in Illinois in 1913 and attended the University of California at Berkeley. Drawn into the socialist movement after the San Francisco general strike, he joined the Workers Party of the United States in 1935 and became a seaman and organizer for the Sailor's Union of the Pacific. In 1938, Lovell was a founding member of the Socialist Workers Party, and played a leading role in the organization for more than five decades. In the early 1950s, Lovell moved to Detroit where he became an auto worker and ran for Governor of Michigan 3 times from 1954-1964. In the late 1960s, he moved to New York City where Lovell served as the Socialist Workers Party's trade union director until Lovell and wife Sarah were expelled from the SWP in 1981. Lovell died on May 1, 1998. The collection includes: correspondence, the bulk of which pertain to Lovell's 1981 expulsion from the SWP; manuscripts of Lovell's numerous articles, reviews, speeches, class lectures, reports for and on the SWP; and topical files that deal with major labor movement events, controversies, and movements.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Frank Lovell 1998. The accession number associated with this gift is 1998.002.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
In December 2025, FOIA Files related to Sarah Lovell were transferred from the National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records (TAM 106). The accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.099.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series. Files in Series I and Series II are arranged chronologically. Files in Series III have not been arranged by an archivist. The series arrangement of the collection is as follows:
I. Correspondence
II. Political activities and writings
III. FOIA files
Biographical Note
Frank Lovell (1913-1998) was born on July 24, 1913, in Ipava, Illinois, a farming town where his father was a local entrepreneur. In the early 1930s Lovell attended the University of California's Berkeley campus, earning a B.A. in philosophy. Drawn into the socialist movement after the San Francisco general strike, he joined the Workers Party of the United States in 1935. He consequently became a seaman and an organizer for the Sailor's Union of the Pacific. In 1938, Lovell was a founding member of the Socialist Workers Party, and played a leading role in the organization for more than five decades. For a number of years he served on national leadership bodies of the SWP, writing extensively for socialist publications on labor issues and other matters. Under the pen-name Frederick Lang he authored a study of seamen's unionism Maritime!(Pioneer Publishers, 1943). In Portland, Oregon in the late 1940s he edited The Defender, a rank-and-file paper opposing the conservatism and anti-left purges in the maritime industry and unions. In the early 1950s Frank moved to Detroit, where he became an auto worker. With George and Dorothea Breitman, Frank and his wife Sarah played a significant role in the Detroit labor and socialist movements of the 1950s and 1960s and Lovell ran for Governor of Michigan on the SWP ticket in 1954, 1958 and 1964. In the late 1960s they moved to New York City, where Frank served as the Socialist Workers Party's trade union director.
In the early 1980s, Frank and Sarah Lovell were among hundreds expelled from the SWP. In December 1983 Lovell initiated Bulletin in Defense of Marxism, first serving as editor, and later on its Board. Lovell was a leading figure of the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, which from 1983 to 1992 sought to bring about unification of all U.S. supporters of the Fourth International. After the group's dissolution, Lovell for a time was involved in another socialist group, Solidarity. In his final years he gave attention to creating and administering the Thomas Giunta Living Trust, named after a veteran Trotskyist seaman whom Frank had befriended some years before. Lovell died on May 1, 1998.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Breitman Papers (TAM 169)
Scope and Content Note
The Papers are organized into three series. Two are arranged chronologically: I. Correspondence; II. Political Activities & Writings. In addition to correspondence, there are published and unpublished writings, Socialist Workers Party and Fourth Internationalist Tendency internal documents, and clippings and other research materials. The focus of most of this material is the labor movement, and the strategies and tactics to be employed by Trotskyist militants. Series III: FOIA Files contains Freedom of Information Act files on Frank and Sarah Lovell.
The bulk of the correspondence is from the years leading up to and following Lovell's 1981 expulsion from the Socialist Workers Party, and much of it concerns the issues and events leading up to his expulsion, the founding of the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, and the founding and publishing of the Bulletin in Defense of Marxism. Series II contains manuscripts of Lovell's numerous articles, reviews, speeches, class lectures, reports for and on the SWP, most concerned with the labor movement. Many of the lectures were given at classes for union militants held around the country. There are also topical files on major labor movement events, controversies, rank and file movements, and on relevant economic topics.
Reports.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Manuscripts for publication.; Lecture notes.; Reviews (document genre); Communism -- United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Fourth Internationalist Tendency (Group); Lovell, Frank; Socialist Workers Party
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: Political Activities and Writings
  - Cannon Material, 1919-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cannon Speeches & Articles [Weissman Collection], 1924-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cannon Speeches & Articles [Weissman Collection], 1946-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Detroit, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mahoney Case Typescript with Cover Letter, 1950, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
  - Cannon Letters, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kerry Letters, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mayoral campaign: Detroit (Lovell), 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - On Publication of Labor's Giant Step, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, Reports, Debates [Detroit], 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - England; Warad/Mills; Lovell/Detroit, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cannon Letters, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Log of Journey, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lovell Report & Talks, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lovell talks and unfinished articles on SWP; Khrushchev's visit; UAW witch-hunt; Attack on Teamsters [Beck finished], 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Reports, Talks, and Branch discussions, 1954-1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Square D Strike material, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Auto Settlement & the general auto situation; 1955 - July 23 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Campaigns: For Supt. of Schools; Against Michigan Senate Bill 1011, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Speeches and Reports, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Speeches and Reports, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Debates and Speeches [Michnik], 1956, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lovell Speeches [CP Crisis]; 1958 - February (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Talks: Detroit, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Cuba Letter [ Militant]; 1960 - April 15 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Lovell/Paul Silver debate - election campaign, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - UAW Material, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Kennedy administration: talks, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Speeches: Michigan campaign & England, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Talks: May Day, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Teamsters probes, government attacks, talks on, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 0.1)
  - Triple Revolution, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Talks on History of Unions - YSA Educational Weekend, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cannon Letters, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Structure and Organizational principles, Party norms, ca.1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - UAW Ford Strike [ Militant articles], 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Labor history, Lovell & others, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Dobbs Correspondence & related material [Dobbs/Maloney, inc], 1967-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Black caucuses in unions: DRUM at Dodge Main by Ed Lee, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Local 160 material: union democracy, black equality, Birch society, etc., 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Reuther/Meany Split: ms. [published in ISR - 1968] (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Auto Industry COLA/Reuther (ts, 56 pp), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mayoral campaign in Detroit: Lovell, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - NY Talks; 1969 - November, 2, 4 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Talks: Chicago & Detroit; 1969 - August (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - UAW Skilled Trades Conference; 1969 - April, 16-17 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Austin, Henry Correspondence - Detroit/NY Talks in Detroit [Leo Bernard killed], 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Disillusionment with Democratic Party, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Meany and Democrats - controversial articles; 1970 - September (Box 4, Folder 17A)
  - Nixon's wage freeze - phase II, ca.1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Summer School NY, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Tour Talks, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Ipava, IL Correspondence - I, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Ipava, IL Correspondence - II, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - UAW, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Introduction to Labor's Giant Step[Unpublished draft], 1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Misc. Reports and Educational Material, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Nixon's wage freeze - talk at uptown branch, NY; 1971 - August 27 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Talk at Welfare rights conference - Bloomington, IN, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Talks: Wage Freeze, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Transitional Program in Minneapolis, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Will steelworkers strike?; 1971 - July 30 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Decline of the CIO: A talk at Atlanta Summer School, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Documents on SWP trade union position tour, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Lovell branch tour: Cleveland Educational Conference, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Lovell branch tour: Talks, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Lovell report to April plenum on tour; 1972 - April (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Minneapolis Summer School, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Nixon wage freeze - phase III (talk); 1972 - January (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Sliding scale of wages & hours; Labor party (talks), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Talks on unions and anti-war movement, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Three Classes on Labor Movement & Teamster Rebellion; 1972 - July 1st (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Two talks on Cochranism, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Classes in Toronto: State of Unions, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mines Forum, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NY Hospital Strike (3 classes); 1973 - November (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pittsburgh Panel; 1973 - May 19 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Prospects for Labor, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - United Farm Workers: sign of 'new' unionism; 1973 - September (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Basic outlines of present trade union policy of SWP; 1974 - July (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Critique of Fourth International Majority position on Labor Action, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Inflation, Unemployment, and Picket lines; 1974 - November (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Interview in London: Wheeler, NUM; 1974 - February (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - A Key emand: sliding scale of wages & hours and fight against inflation; 1974 - July (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Marxist approach to Labor Movement: the Labor Party; 1974 - July (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Material on British Miners' Strike & Downfall of Tory Government (picket line), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - NY Printers strike and contract settlement [Brooklyn Forum]; 1974 - May 31 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - State of the Unions; 1974 - April 26 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Talks on Mine Strike (NY), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Crisis of Capitalist Economy & Problems of Unions - Pittsburgh Talk; 1975 - April 26 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Material to Maxine Williams, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Summer School - 3 class series, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Union work today [talk in NY, Seattle, etc.], 1975 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Unionism and Socialism (talk); 1975 - November 7 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - National Maritime Union, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Book reviews: Reuther & Marquart, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Prospects for Socialism (review), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Labor party, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Carter's first year: Talk; 1977 - December (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Educational Conference - Boston; 1977 - July (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Militant Articles (before editing); 1977 - April/May (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - State of the Unions: Talk at Wayne State University; 1977 - February 22 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - SWP/Labor Party Question [pamphlet], 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Teamsters: Williams Trial, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Battle of the Myths - Social Democrats vs. Stalinists; 1978 - October 6 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Keeping the Faith- Book Review about Sleeping Car Porters [unpublished], 1978 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Militant at 50 - New Orleans; 1978 - December 2 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - On Union Strategy - 3 talks, Oberlin, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Querio, Ruth Memorial - Pittsburgh; 1978 - December 13 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - SWP Election Campaign - Chicago, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Talk at Bronx Branch Forum; 1978 - January 13 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Three Political Currents in the Labor Movement, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Three Talks on Union Work, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Political Currents in the Labor Movement; Building Class - Struggle Left Wing [New Orleans]; 1978 - December (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Transitional Program [ISR], 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - SWP Party Structure - Principles & Constitutions box 10, 1978-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Carter Administration's 1979 Wage/Price Guidelines - a 3-part series in the Militant; 1979 - May/June (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - GSTQ Labor Party Interview - Quebec [Group Socialiste des Travailleurs du Quebec]; 1979 - February (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Hansen, Joseph Memorial Meetings; 1979 - January (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Meany, George: Profile; 1979 - November (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Overtime - 3 part series [ Militant]; 1979 - April (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - UAW: Then and Now, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Union Work and the Labor Party idea [Discussion Bulletin]; 1979 - July 3 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Why American Workers Need a Labor Party, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - The World Political Situation and Tasks of the F.I (unpublished review); 1979 - August (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Source Material and Articles on Chrysler Bankruptcy, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Auto Union gets New Leadership, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Auto & Doug Fraser, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Black Detroit & Rise of UAW - A Review [ Militant]; 1980 - March (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Dobbs Mss Revolutionary Continuity, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Farrand, Andy, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Ford/Marx; 1980 - May 17 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Hormel, ca.1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Keely, John Memorial; 1980 - August 22 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Kirkland, Lane, Meany's Heir [ Militant]; 1980 - March 22 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Labor History by Paul LeBlanc, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Labor Party Forum - Pittsburgh; 1980 - June 1st (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Legacy of George Meany; 1980 - March 18th (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Lovell Reports, Talks, Drafts, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - National Maritime Union (see also box 5, folder 25), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Productivity, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Recent Developments in Labor [UAW Convention - a non event]; 1980 - July 4 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Review: History of Russian Revolution [ Militant], 1980 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Second National TUAD Conference, Gary, IN; 1980 - June (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Smith, Stan - Campaign, San Francisco [tactic of critical support], 1980 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Socialism: Utopian, and Scientific, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Trucks Law Fight in Michigan, 1952 - 1956 [ Militant]; 1980 - March (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Why American Workers Need Labor Party [Denver, Phoenix], 1980 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Stalinism and Unions [Oberlin], 4 Classes Series, 1980, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Labor Party, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Maloney, Jack File, 1980, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Socialist Workers Party: National Executive Committee, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Institute for Labor Education & Research, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Kerry, Karolyn Memorial; 1981 - February 22 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - LeBlanc, Lovell - misc., 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Matter of Perspective [Discussion Bulletin]; 1981 - July 10 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Mini, Norman testifies, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Oberlin Convention, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Stalinism & Unions: Review Material, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Stalinism & Unions - Review of 3 books, Ms.; 1981 - February (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - SWP National Committee: Minutes, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - SWP Plenum; 1981 - November (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Teamster & TDU: Nader Group Investigation, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Transportation: Strike, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Coal Negotiations, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Convention: Discussions, Reports, Reading Lists, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Labor Problems (before Chrysler), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Radicalization in Seattle, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Workers Party: Political Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Socialist Workers Party: Political Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - UAW Contract (Chrysler/Ford), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Weinstein/Henderson Tendency in SWP National Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - California convention of SWP, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Chrysler: Clippings, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Fraser, Clara, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Hard times - problems for labor, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Lippman Labor Party Pamphlet, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Lovell/Bloom reports - February-March Plenum, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Lovell/Bloom resolutions, motions, motivations - SWP Plenum; 1982 - Feb.-March (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - May/June meeting of IEC, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Montreal - Discussion- Lovell-Bloom / IEC; 1982 - January (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Notes (SWP, factional, etc), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - PB Minutes #20, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - PC/PB prepares for Oberlin, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Post - Oberlin PB Minutes and Related Material, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Post Oberlin PB Minutes & Related Material, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Sources - Party tactics in unions and politics, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Stalinism and the American Labor Movement - 4 part series, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Steelworkers, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - SWP plenum material [post-Oberlin], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - SWP plenum material [post-Oberlin], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - SWP referenda, other internal documents, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - SWP Feb-Mar Plenum: Kit material, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - SWP Feb-Mar Plenum: notes, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - SWP Feb-Mar Plenum: PC & PB minutes, etc., 1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - SWP Feb-Mar Plenum: PC & PB minutes, etc., 1982 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Teamster Contract, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Three Mile Island / anti-nuke & rate payers revolt [Seattle connection], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Union givebacks / company takebacks - tss, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Assassination of Union Leaders in Seattle; Assorted Material on Unions, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Fourth Internationalist Tendency Correspondence (Anti-War), 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - PC Minutes - Post December 1982 Plenum, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Reports: Lovell/Bloom to PC February-March 1982; Plenum & Continued through March 9th, 1983, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - UAW, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Suspensions of SWP - NC members Weinstein, Lovell, Bloom, Henderson, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Democratic Centralism & Organizational Norms...incl #8 Bulletin [See 1982 Discussion File], 1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Feeley, Dianne - Letter against Expulsion, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Feeley, Dianne - What Common Learned in the Early Communist Party, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - May Plenum, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Pre-Conference Discussion-Preparing for Launching of Socialist Action, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Action version of differences with BIDOM [Mocker Letter] & Refutation Documents, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - SWP PC Minutes, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - SWP PC Minutes, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Unemployment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Unemployment, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Unpublished Articles for the Militant, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Action: disassociation letter, list of opposition documents. Draft theses & World Congress, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - State of the Unions, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Bureau - United Secretariat, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Chronicle of Events - Lovell, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Results & Meaning of Presidential Election, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - SWP Amendments to 1984 Resolution (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Which Road Defends Your Class Interests (Lovell talk), 1984 (Box 9, Folder 17A)
  - Cannon Material [New Book] - GB, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Cuba, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Lovell Reports, Talks, Drafts, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - New Zealand Correspondence - Jurrian Benedien vs. Socialist Action, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - United Secretariat, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Crisis of the US Labor Movement and the Left, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Fourth Internationalist Tendency: 3rd National Conference - Minutes & Records, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - SWP/Pathfinder vs. George Breitman, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Fourth Internationalist Tendency, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 25A)
  - Correspondence: Donations to the George Weissman Collection at the Walter P. Reuther Library, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 26)